All right, so today's דף *daf* is ט"ו *Tes Vav*, 16,
and we pick up on the bottom of ט"ו עמוד ב' *Tes
Vav Amud Bet* where we were talking about we quoted פסוקים pesukim,
*pesukim* about the return when they built the began building the second
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash *Beit HaMikdash*, how they were crying, you know,
remembering how great the glory of the first בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash*
was, and of course the end of the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*, גדול
יהיה כבוד הבית האחרון מן הראשון gadol yihiyeh kevod habayit ha'acharon min
harishon. *Gadol yihiyeh kevod habayit ha'acharon min harishon*, although that wasn't quoted
from the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, that in the end, you know, or
that the glory of the second בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash* will go
beyond that, will be greater than that of the first בית המקדש
*Beit HaMikdash*. And but somehow that led the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* now
into quoting a משנה Mishna, *Mishnah* in סוטה *Sotah* which also sort
of reflects back to the greatness of previous generations and יוסף בן
יועזר איש צרידה *Yosef ben Yoezer Ish Tzeredah* and יוסף בן יוחנן
איש ירושלים *Yosef ben Yochanan Ish Yerushalayim* as the last of the
אשכולות *Eshkolot*, those that had everything in them, which רש"י Rashi *Rashi*
said was תורה Torah *Torah*, יראת חטא yirat chet *Yirat Chet*, and
גמילות חסדים *Gemilut Chasadim*. And the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* now is focusing
on the תורה Torah, *Torah* aspect and saying that after them nobody
learned תורה Torah, *Torah* through them you would they were learning תורה
Torah, *Torah* like משה רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu. *Moshe Rabbeinu*, which apparently means
that they were passing it down perfectly. So now the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* is has been challenging that, so let's take a look.
One, two,
three, sorry, no, let's take a look.
Okay, three lines down from the wide lines. So the גמרא Gemara?
*Gemara* says, so already mentioning that some הלכות halachos *halachot* were forgot
during the mourning for משה Moshe *Moshe*, and it says, okay, but
the ones they remembered they passed down perfectly. So the גמרא Gemara,
*Gemara* says, והתניא *Veha tanya*, do we not teach in a ברייתא
Baraisa *Baraita*, משמת משה Moshe, *mishemet Moshe*, after משה רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu.
*Moshe Rabbeinu* died, how did they deal with debates? So אם רבו
מטמאין טמא אם רבו מטהרין טהור *im rabu metame'in tamei, im rabu
metaherin tahor*. If they took it to a vote, if there was
a majority that said טמא *tamei*, they decided it was טמא *tamei*,
whatever the case was, or if the majority said it was טהור
*tahor*, they decided it was טהור *tahor*, meaning they went by majority
vote. So you see
that there were questions that arose, and it seems like it arose
even right after משה Moshe. *Moshe*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says,
ליבא דאימעיט מיגמר הוה גמירי להו כמשה רבינו *Liba de'imat, migmar hava
gemiri lehu keMoshe Rabbeinu*. It says, yes, in terms of
their ability to analyze or I would sort of say, take some
little license from the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, to apply it to new
cases, those were things that they did not necessarily were able to
do without there being debate. But in terms of the question of
being able to be transmitters and pass down what משה Moshe *Moshe*
said, there was no question about the perfect passing down of everything
that they had received. The debates were not about questions about what
they received, the questions were about sort of applying it to things
that they had not received. Now רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says that the
questions here were trying to remember those הלכות halakhot *halachot* that they
forgot. But either way, the point is,
saying it that way sort of emphasizes that or sort of makes
it sound like, you know, if you have perfect transmission you'll never
have any questions, which as we know is not true. A lot
of הלכה halacha, *halacha* is not about what you received but is
about applying it to new cases, not about the transmission. But anyway
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says again, what they received they passed down
perfectly. Things they didn't receive, there there were debates, but what they
received they passed down perfectly. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says,
דמתניתא תנא Tanna, *de'matnita tana*, we taught in the ברייתא Baraisa *Baraita*,
כל האשכולות שעמדו לישראל מימות משה Moshe, עד שמת יוסף בן יועזר
איש צרידה *kol ha'eshkolot she'amdu leYisrael miymot Moshe ad shemet Yosef ben
Yoezer Ish Tzeredah*, all the אשכולות *Eshkolot* again these people that were,
you know, these perfect leaders or complete leaders I should say, from
the time of משה Moshe *Moshe* until יוסף בן יועזר *Yosef ben
Yoezer*, לא היה בהם שום דופי shum dofi, *lo hayah bahem shum
dofi*, there was never there was not even the slightest דופי dofi,
*dofi*, problem, anything lacking. מכאן ואילך היה בהם שום דופי shum dofi.
*Mikan va'eilach hayah bahem shum dofi*, afterwards there were, you know, things
weren't perfect, there were problems.
Okay, so but were they still אשכולות *Eshkolot* though?
No, well apparently not, these were the end of the אשכולות *Eshkolot*.
Okay, so let's take a look. So apparently דופי *dofi* here does
not get into the question about the תורה Torah, *Torah* aspect, the
perfection of their knowledge or of their transmission, presumably here we're sort
of raising the other aspect of the אשכולות *Eshkolot* in terms of
their behavior, their character, their observance of מצוות mitzvot *mitzvot*. So let's
take a look what the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says. What's אשכולות *Eshkolot*?
אשכולות *Eshkolot* is again the phrase used yesterday, literally means like clusters,
like a cluster of grapes, but the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* translated it
as איש שהכל בו *ish shekol bo*, a person that is sort
of complete, רש"י Rashi, *Rashi* says has תורה Torah, *Torah*, has יראת
חטא yiras cheit, *Yirat Chet*, has גמילות חסדים *Gemilut Chasadim*. So let's
take a look. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, והתניא *Veha tanya*,
but one minute, we taught in a ברייתא *Baraita*, מעשה בחסיד אחד
שהיה גונח מלבו *ma'aseh bechasid echad shehayah gone'ach milibo*, there was a
certain righteous individual that he had like some heart, you know, he
was moaning from his heart, he had some heart pains or chest
pains, ושאלו לרופאים *vesha'alu lerofim*, and they asked doctors, ואמרו *ve'amru*, and
they said, אין לו תקנה עד שינק חלב רותח משחרית *ein lo
takanah ad sheyinak chalav rote'ach sheshacharit*, the only way he can sort
of deal with his problem is to every morning drink hot milk,
and hot milk here basically means milk that was just milked from
the animal, so you know, to have the animal's body temperature, so
it's still hot, so freshly milked.
So how did they deal with it? They הביאו לו עז וקשרו
לו בכרעי מיטתו. So they brought him a goat, he tied it
to the, to his bed post or to the legs of his
bed, והיה יונק ממנה חלב vehaya yonek mimena chalav
and he would every morning he would milk it, it actually sounds
like he would squirt it right into his mouth every morning from
this goat. And that's how he dealt with his health issue. Okay.
ולמחר נכנסו חבריו לבקרו. ulemachar nichnesu chaverav levakro. The next day his
friends came to visit him, maybe they were just coming to pay
a, you know, just visit him for a friendly visit or maybe
he was still sick and in bed, he was still recuperating. Anyway,
כיוון שראו העז, keivan she-ra'u ha-ez, when they saw the goat in
his house, אמרו, amru, they said, ליסטים מזויין בתוך ביתו ואנו נכנסים
לבקרו? listim mezuyan betoch beito ve-anu nichnasim levakro? This person has armed
robbers in his house and we're going to come visit him? Because
as you might know, the rabbis were very opposed to the raising
of small grazing animals, sheep and goats in Israel, because they would
completely sort of destroy, you know, the grass and the ground, especially
if you don't move them around, you know, widely and they stay
in one place, they eat the grass to the very bottom and
they are very much hurt, hurt the land. So they forbade people
to raise grazing animals in Israel, especially, you know, in sort of
settled areas like in the cities as opposed to, you know, out,
you know, on the, on the hills. Anyway, so they said how
can we go to this person's house? Look what he's doing, he's
violating this rule and he's having this goat and the fact that
he was doing it for health reasons did not seem to sway
them.
So there seems to be a little part of this missing which
the Tosefta adds, הניחו ויצאו. henicho ve-yatza'u. So they left.
And then כשמת, keshe-met, after he died, ישבו ובדקו, yashvu u-vadku, they
looked into sort of this person's actions, ולא מצאו בו עוון אלא
של אותה עז בלבד. velo matzu bo avon ela shel osah ez
bilvad. And they saw that the only thing this person ever did
wrong in his life was this goat, that he had this goat
in his house as a way of solving his problem. Again, what's
funny is that they didn't move from their, from their position that
he was totally wrong, like that was not a legitimate reason to...
And they knew he was sick!
I know, that's... I know, I know, that's, I'm saying, that's, that's
like, I think that's our take on this story is the Gemara's
take is all, he would have been perfect were it not for
this one thing. And our take is what was so wrong about
that one thing? I mean he was sick! Exactly. פיקוח נפש pikuach
nefesh though. I understand, you know, but anyway, but it seems like
there was maybe a bigger like policy issue that it was maybe
be a license to other people to do it. I mean you
could keep one goat in your house and feed it stuff without
having it graze the land and have that destructive impact. Anyway, ואף
הוא בשעת מיתתו, ve-af hu bish'at mitato, even when he died, this
person, אמר יודע אני בעצמי, amar yode'a ani be-atzmi, I know about
myself, שאין בי עוון אלא של אותה עז בלבד, she-ein bi avon
ela shel osah ez bilvad, that I only have the sin of
that one goat, wait wait, שעברתי על דברי חבריי. she-avarti al divrei
chaverai. And now it's interesting the way he frames it. The problem
is is that I went against, you know, what they had said,
what my colleagues had said. שהרי אמרו חכמים, sheharei amru chachamim, for
the sages said, אין מגדלין בהמה דקה בארץ ישראל. ein megadlin behemah
dakah be-eretz yisrael.
You do not raise grazing animals in Israel. Okay, so again it's
sort of interesting, you know, maybe it's the problem was a חטא
chet or an עוון, avon, a sin, but you know, question about
like how intrinsically wrong was it or was it wrong because of
the policies that had been set and because of sort of what
it showed about respecting sort of the rabbinic rule. Anyway, that's the
story.
So how do they get the sacrificial animals if they don't raise
them in Israel?
Yeah, so that's right. So the point is is that it's really
more of,
it's a lot more about raising it בישוב, be-yishuv, like in the
sort of like in the city area rather than, you know, way
out on the hills and having them, you know, sort of move
around a lot so they don't stay in any one place. Okay,
so the Gemara says וקיימא לן, ve-kaima lan, כל היכא דאמר מעשה
בחסיד אחד, kol heicha de-amar ma'aseh be-chasid echad, whenever it says a
story of a חסיד, chasid, או רבי יהודה בן בבא או רבי
יהודה ברבי אילעאי. o rabbi yehuda ben bava o rabbi yehuda berabi
ilai. It was either Rabbi Yehuda ben Bava or it was Rabbi
Yehuda berabi Ilai. Now why is that a problem? דרבנן בתר יוסי
בן יועזר שני דרי דרי הוו. derabbanan batar yose ben yoezer sheneidarei
darei havu. And those rabbis, those two Rabbi Yehudas, were many many
generations after Yose ben Yoezer. So why is that all a question?
Because we said,
right, so,
so they, we said that after those two, you know, all of
the great sages or all of the great leaders of Israel never
had, you know, always had דופי, a problem. And here the Gemara
interestingly is quoting this as an example that you see that there
could have been great rabbis or great leaders after those two that
also didn't have any real sins. So it's interesting, although the story
is that this person had said and they said at the time
he was just, I did have this one sin, the Gemara's bringing
this as an example of somebody that didn't have שום דופי, shum
dofi. right? If that's the only sin he had, then this was
somebody who didn't have שום דופי. shum dofi So how can you
say... See it's not so bad. Because that's not the part you're
going to get upset about. Wait, it'll be another part you're going
to get upset about. Anyway, so you see if that's the only
sin, it was another person who didn't have שום דופי. How could
you say that after these two, you know, there was never, nobody
else was as perfect in terms of their sort of יראת חטא
or שמירת מצוות? shmirat mitzvot? So the Gemara says like this, אמר
רב
יוסף, amar rav yosef, so Rav Yosef said.
דופי של סמיכה קתני. dofi shel smicha ktani. Now we're back to
תלמוד תורה. Talmud Torah. In terms of like greatness in terms of
observance and יראת חטא, yes, there were similar after that generation. But
back to the תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah theme, there was meaning we
we mean about sort of the there weren't problems in terms of
their learning. Now why does he mention סמיכה? smicha? סמיכה smicha is
not the סמיכה smicha you give to rabbis here. סמיכה smicha means
as you the earliest debates that are
recorded from the sages, which even precedes the like sort of what
they're called you know רב Rav so on, the rabbinic period, it's
when they were still the זוגות, zugot, is debates about whether you
can do סמיכה smicha when you bring an animal on יום טוב.
Yom Tov. So that was debates and that went generation to generation
through the זוגות, zugot, questions about doing סמיכה smicha on animals on
certain קרבנות korbanot on יום טוב. Yom Tov. So what it says
is that did not start until after יוסי בן יועזר איש צרידה
Yosef ben Yoezer ish Tzreida and יוסי בן יוחנן איש ירושלים. Yosef
ben Yochanan ish Yerushalayim. So the whole areas of when questions arose
in הלכה, halacha. you know, even this very first thing which seemed
to have been the only question for many many generations, you know,
that only occurred after these two. So we're back to our theme
that only after these two did questions arise, before then the transmission
was perfect.
You know, I thought it says and you're saying it doesn't mean
the סמיכה smicha because it was interesting because because remember יהודה בן
בבא Yehuda ben Bava ימלא
זכור איש לטוב yimaleh zachur ish letov because if not because without
him ישכחו yishkachu whatever because you know he did the whole thing
of סמיכה. smicha. Remember that? He took the people to...
Yeah, yeah, but we're not talking about...
That would be very interesting that it talks...
No, no, no, that's much later. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
ויוסי בן יועזר גופיה מי פליגי בסמיכה? veYosef ben Yoezer gufei mi
pligi bismicha?
One minute, יוסי בן יועזר Yosef ben Yoezer himself was the first
person who was part of that סמיכה smicha controversy. Okay, again, not
the סמיכה smicha controversy of the other context. But anyway, part of
that question about סמיכה smicha on קרבנות. korbanot. So the גמרא Gemara.
says כי פליג בה בסוף שני. ki plig bah besof shnei. When
did they when did those debates arose if at when did he
at the end of his life? דבצר ליבא, debatzer liba, that that's
when sort of the intellect or you know their their knowledge started
becoming faulty. But till the end of his life, like you used
to say... Yeah, so that's the question that we're going on with
which I've sort of been a little bit skirting is is that
question. Let me just say this. So until the end of his
life, you know, there was never any debates in הלכה. halacha The
debates in הלכה halacha only arose after they died and that's what
it means שום דופי after that point was only when debates arose
or towards the end of his life. But he was the last
generation or they two were the last generation before there started being
becoming so many debates. Now what is sort of now with saying
all of that, the question sort of still arises here that you
know the גמרא Gemara first of all did say before that there
were debates about other things. It said that they were debating right
after the death of משה רבינו. Moshe Rabbeinu, But they were debating
things about the הלכות halachos, that משה Moshe. that they forgot and
that they were debating you know so and one also wonders in
this general as a question, you know, really this gets and it's
important because this is framed in the גמרא Gemara about the issue
of like כבוד הבית האחרון, kvod habayis ha'acharon, you know, sort of
romanticizing the past. So one sort of really wonders, you know, and
this is a major debate in the ראשונים Rishonim about how to
think about this. Why are there so many debates in the גמרא?
Gemara Right? Why and this actually was a critique, a major critique
that the what do you call it the...
הקשן? hakashan? No, the Karaites opposed to the rabbis. You're saying you
have תורה שבעל פה. Torah shebe'al peh. You're saying you have a
מסורה. masorah. How could you have a מסורה masorah if every single
page of your תלמוד Talmud is filled with debates? Obviously, you have
a faulty transmission and it's a faulty transmission, we can't we can't
trust any of it. That was a debate that the Karaites raised
and the question is how to respond to it. So actually, you
know, there were some that were basically said yeah, the reason for
debates as is implied by this גמרא, Gemara you know, is because
things were forgotten and that is the reason for debates. I don't
know exactly how they answer the Karaites response, they could basically say
okay, but there's many many things we agree upon, with some of
the things we debate but 90% of the basic parameters we all
we all know we all agree. But basically there's an approach that's
reinforced by a certain number of גמרות Gemarot that basically say yeah,
the debates arose, you know, like for the גמרא Gemara example, the
גמרא Gemara about בית שמאי ובית הלל. Beis Shammai uBeis Hillel. It
says, you know, it
says משרבו תלמידי בית שמאי ובית הלל שלא שמשו כל צרכן, mishe'rabu
talmidei Beis Shammai uBeis Hillel shelo shimshu kol tzarchan, when you had
all of these students that did not spend enough time with their
rebbeim and enough time getting their traditions, that's when you had all
of these debates. All the debates exploded when people were not paying
as much attention and when people were not being as good as
passing down the מסורה. masorah. That's sort of what this גמרא Gemara.
suggests, that that's the source of debates is that you forget things.
By the way, I should say that the context of this where
this is leading up to is as you know in our משנה,
mishna. there's a debate about, you know, the חמש חטאות המתות, chamesh
chataos hamesos, which generally is understood, right, to be הלכה למשה מסיני.
halacha leMoshe miSinai. So part of this is saying how did debates
arise even in things of the transmission, things get forgotten, debates arise
and so on. And that sort of seems to be and if
we'd remember everything there would be no debates.
הרמב"ם haRambam completely disagrees with that. הרמב"ם haRambam even both philosophically and
also also, you know, it serves as a very powerful response to
the Karaites, says absolutely not. The transmission was perfect. There was never
any questions about transmission. Everything that was הלכה למשה מסיני halacha leMoshe
miSinai was completely... Of course big problems because there seems to be
exactly against that in this גמרא Gemara and other גמרות, Gemaras, but
okay, that was very important for the רמב"ם Rambam to claim nothing,
there was never a problem in transmission, that's the response to the
Karaites. What are all the debates? The debates are not in transmission,
the debates are in application. We know what the law on the
book says. The question is, how do you define, apply it to
cases that haven't been addressed? How do you, how do you understand
the parameters that haven't been passed down, that haven't been explicated? So
the debates were in everything that the transmission didn't address. And that's
what... Right, so that's what the רמב"ם Rambam says. That's a very
sort of powerful approach, it's one that's very resonant. But again, you
know, it's something that sort of, you know, is not so much
present in this גמרא, Gemara which seems to frame it as a
ירידת הדורות yeridat hadorot as a failing now that we have debates.
But okay, one minute. Anyway, as I will say though, and maybe
this is me just reading into the גמרא, Gemara I admit that
from the beginning, is, you know, given that we quoted the comparison
to the first בית המקדש and how terrible things are, whatever, you
know, within that story there's a subtext of, right, the response to
that, גדול יהיה כבוד הבית האחרון gadol yihiyeh kevod habayit ha'acharon. מן
הראשון. So I, I wonder because there are other גמרות Gemarot that
actually do say very clearly that, you know, that, you know, that,
you know, that is the goal of being a great Talmudist, rabbi,
etc., halakhist, is it about just knowing everything and passing it down,
or is it about using your intellect to derive and understand? Like,
which is like רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva as opposed to רבי אליעזר,
Rabbi Eliezer, who's basically is framed as somebody who just received and
passed down and so on. And the גמרא Gemara clearly weighs in
favor of the רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva approach. So I sort of
wonder whether at the surface saying, "Oy, it's so terrible, we forgot,
and you know, all these questions arose and we don't pass down
perfectly," if there might be, and I may be way overreading it,
but a hidden subtext of, you know, actually maybe there's a גדול
יהיה כבוד הבית האחרון. Maybe actually the degree to which now it
is this sort of creative intellect and that's sort of what makes
תורה שבעל פה. Torah Shebe'al Peh. Yes, in a way it's not
as great as the past, but in a way it's greater. Okay,
but I think that's me a little bit overreading, but anyway I
wanted to say that. So anyway, but, but this גמרא Gemara certainly
seems to very much emphasize the approach against the רמב"ם Rambam that
all questions are just because of things that we forgot. Although the
רמב"ם's Rambam's approach really I think makes a lot more sense. You
don't, even if you remember everything, you know, not everything was said
at the, was said at the beginning. So you, you know, obviously
you need debates to, to compensate for that.
I mean, even for 2,000 years it was never, whatever long it
was, it was never a question about application?
Well, that's I think a general question, right, to ask, you know,
forgetting the רמב"ם, Rambam, unless you actually take a very, you know,
sort of mystical approach that every single question that was ever future
to derive was already handed out to משה, Moshe was already and,
and everything was transmitted from the beginning, right, which also finds support
in the גמרא. Gemara But it's very hard for a, you know,
rational person to believe that that's really it. So...
And the רמב"ם Rambam was very much a rationalist.
Yeah, I understand. So anyway, that's at least, so yes, so those
are those issues. But this גמרא Gemara emphasizes what was forgotten. Okay,
and...
And it's based on just about what was forgotten.
And that the implication of this גמרא Gemara is that the only
reason debates arose is because things began to be forgotten.
And that means that they were less אשכול. eshkol.
Right, and that's why it was a ירידת הדורות yeridat hadorot after
this period because that's where things happen when things began to be
forgotten. So let's take a look as the גמרא Gemara continues. So
now we're going to focus on trying to recover what we forgot,
because, you know, there were these things that were forgotten at the
time of משה רבינו. Moshe Rabbeinu So let's take a look. אמר
רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, בגופא, begufa, let's
go back to what we said before. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל,
Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, שלושת אלפים הלכות נשתכחו בימי אבלו של
משה. shloshet alafim halakhot nishtakechu bimei evlo shel Moshe. 3,000 הלכות halachos,
were forgotten at the time of משה. Moshe So they wanted to
get those back. So אמרו לו ליהושע, amru lo l'Yehoshua, they said
to יהושע, Yehoshua, שאל, she'al, ask God, let's get, let's recover them,
go back to God, ask him, you know, go, go ask him
what we forgot. Go to the source. אמר להם, Amar lahem, לא
בשמים היא. lo bashamayim hi. Sorry, after משה Moshe, we can't get,
God can't contribute to the process. אמרו לו לשמואל, Amru lo l'Shmuel,
so they said to שמואל, Shmuel, שאל, she'al, go and ask God.
So אמר להם, amar lahem, אלה המצוות, eleh hamitzvot, these are the
מצוות mitzvot that God commanded משה, Moshe אלה הם, eleh hem, these
are them, and, you know, full stop. You can't add to these
מצוות afterwards, you can't get any more information from God.
But they didn't let the matter rest until שמואל הנביא? Shmuel HaNavi?
Who knows.
We'll... Anyway, שאין נביא רשאי לחדש דבר מעתה. she'ein navi rashai l'chadesh
davar me'ata. After משה רבינו, Moshe Rabbeinu? you cannot innovate. Now, of
course that's a little funny because you could say, "Fine, we're not
innovating, we're recovering." But, you know, the answer לא בשמים היא lo
bashamayim hi seems to be a better answer. But anyway, says, "I'm
sorry, you know, going to God is no longer part of the
process." אמר רבי יצחק נפחא, Amar Rabbi Yitzchak Nafcha, אף חטאת שמתו
בעליה נשתכחה בימי אבלו של משה. af chatat shemetu ba'aleha nishtakecha bimei
evlo shel Moshe. Okay, and this is tying it in and we'll
tie it in again, our issue about what's the story about a
חטאת chatat that the owner died and do you let it die,
do you let it graze? Now we talked about the debate about
what happens by the ציבור, tzibbur, you know, if the ציבור tzibbur
is נתכפרו באחר. nitkapru be'acher. But what we're going to see a
little later today is, and actually the גרסא girsa of the שיטה
מקובצת Shita Mekubetzet says not שמתו shemetu but שנתכפרו בעליה, shenitkapru ba'aleha,
tying it directly into our משנה. mishna That's the debate about what
a ציבור tzibbur does if, you know, if they brought another קרבן,
korban, does the חטאת chatat graze or die? That exact debate in
the משנה mishnah was one of those things that was forgotten. But
not a יחיד? yachid? Right, right, right. Exactly what he says, but
we'll see later today that there are that there are opinions that
even even the general הלכה halacha. of the five חטאות chataos that
die and which are those five or were they really five or
were they really four and we don't know and so on, even
those הלכות, halachos some of them were forgotten. Okay, so even the
exact debate in our משנה mishnah. or one of the aspects of
this of these הלכות, halachos, even about the individual, that was one
of the things that was forgotten, tying it into our whole משנה.
mishnah, That's hard to imagine they were forgotten because it was only
40 years at the maximum. When did משה Moshe, die?
They were... 40 days! It says וימי אבלו של משה, v'yemei evlo
shel Moshe, while they were mourning for משה.
Moshe, But they didn't remember the practice? We assume they were bringing
חטאים... chata'im...
But how many times did you have חטאת שמתו בעליה chatas shemesu
ba'aleha or חטאת שנתכפרו באחר chatas sheniskapru ba'acher for for 40 days?
Over a course of 40 days? No, no, no, it's saying that
it was forgotten in the 40 days from the time משה Moshe
רבינו died.
Is that what they experienced? Their memories were wiped out?
It's interesting. I mean, how often do those of- do those actual
things happen? It's an interesting... Maybe it happened. Yeah, it's a good
point. You know, but it happened to one rare individual- I don't
know, it's a good question.
You know, I mean, think of the effects when there was the
עגל הזהב egel hazahav when משה Moshe didn't come for one day.
In other words, what was his- his- how involved they were with
him
as...
How dependent they were on him. So they weren't really- so even
when
they were mour- I mean, right, how deep the mourning could have
been.
Right, right.
What does it mean that they forgot? Their memories went? They all
had...
Well, how many people could remember all the things that were taught
anyway? You know, I mean, basically we're saying if 3,000 הלכות halachos.
were forgotten, I mean, we're saying like, you know, that in- you
know, other than תורה שבכתב, Torah shebichtav, nothing was written down. Maybe
he never taught it. They... No, that it's not saying. It's saying
they forgot. But still, I mean, I think your question is to
the degree that it was acted upon. If it wasn't acted upon,
you're trying to remember all of the Oral תורה Torah in your
head, right? So, and I think the point is true that they
were so heavily dependent on משה Moshe and, you know, and sort
of in that whole sort of tragic aftermath period, so it's not
a surprise, right? I had a friend once, a חברותא, chavrusa, who
said, he says, you know, the גמרא Gemara says, והיו הדברים האלה
אשר אנכי מצוך היום... v'hayu hadvarim ha'eleh asher anochi metzavcha hayom... no,
it says ושננתם לבניך, v'shinantam l'vanecha, שיהיו משוננים מחודדים בפיך. she'yehu meshunanim
m'chudadim b'ficha. They have to be sharp in your mouth. Okay? And-
and- and so he says, שיהיו מחודדים בפיך, she'yehu m'chudadim b'ficha, that
I'm not able to fulfill. The other דרשה, drasha, which says, יהיו
בכל יום בעיניך כחדשים, hayu b'chol yom b'einecha k'chadashim, every day it
should be like something new, that I have no problem with. Every
time I read it, it's like something new to me. So anyway,
so not everybody- you know, to remember all of תורה שבעל פה,
Torah sheba'al peh, we have it written down and we have a
hard time remembering it. So anyway, that's not a problem. The question
is how often was it acted upon? But it's a rare case.
I don't think that that necessarily, you know, is a- would be
something that it would have been internalized. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
here is tying it into the point of our משנה, Mishna this
was one of the things that was forgotten. Now, we're not done
with the story. אמר ליה פנחס, Amar lei Pinchas, they said to
פנחס, Pinchas, שאל. she'al. Okay,
so go- go ahead. אמר לא בשמים היא, Amar, lo bashamayim hi,
sorry, I
can't help you, לא בשמים היא. lo bashamayim hi. אמרו ליה לאלעזר,
Amru lei l'Elazar, שאל, she'al, they said to אלעזר, Elazar, ask. אמר
להם אלה המצות שאין נביא רשאי לחדש דבר מעתה. Amar lahem, eileh
hamitzvos she'ein navi rashai l'chadesh davar mei'atah. Same point.
Now,
it's interesting that it breaks up, right, יהושע Yehoshua and שמואל Shmuel
from- from-
from פנחס Pinchas and אלעזר. Elazar. And I think that the difference
is that יהושע Yehoshua and שמואל, Shmuel, although שמואל Shmuel was also
a נביא, navi, but he was still also a political leader. So,
you know, on the one hand, you could sort of see that
first they went to their- and יהושע Yehoshua was also a נביא,
navi, but first they went basically to their political leadership and- and
they said, no, you know, can't help you. Then they went to
the people that actually were supposed to have a
direct communication with God, that was their primary function, actually, especially if
you think about the fact that in this week's פרשה parsha we
read about אורים ותומים, Urim v'Tumim, ושאלו במשפט האורים לפני ה', v'shalo
b'mishpat ha'Urim lifnei Hashem, you ask God things through the אורים ותומים.
Urim v'Tumim. Who wore the אורים ותומים? Urim v'Tumim? כהן גדול, Kohen
Gadol, אלעזר Elazar and afterwards פנחס. Pinchas. So that's a very different
type of a question. Maybe that's exactly what you're there for. So
they didn't like the answer. You know, the answer was a principled
position. But of course, if you don't like- I'm sorry, that's not
part of the process. If you don't like the answer, you ask
somebody else, maybe you'll get an answer you like better. And maybe,
maybe they're really not able to do it. Let's go ask somebody
who has a direct line to God. And they get the same
answer. Now, there are different גרסאות girsos here, by the way, about
what order the גמרא Gemara presents these in. It may be there
were other versions where it presents it in a chronological order. But
anyway, I think it's interesting the way it's grouped within our גמרא.
Gemara I mean, you have one that's grouped the two different answers
together.
That's my point.
No, no, no, the גמרא Gemara first says לא בשמים היא lo
bashamayim hi and the other one says... I understand. And the other
one says...
yeah. Okay, but anyway, right, anyway, I think it's for the reasons
I said, that they were very different types of- of roles that
they were playing and they were hoping to get a different answer.
They asked the political leadership, they were also a נביא. navi. I
don't know, they're also- because those are the people that they most
identified with the role of משה, Moshe whereas אלעזר Elazar and פנחס
Pinchas were more identified with the role of אהרן. Aharon. Right, but
משה Moshe was the- sort of- was the- both the political head
and the one that had the direct line to God. Right, after
משה, Moshe although, you know, obviously שמואל Shmuel also was very, very
much a נביא, navi, not just a- whatever, יהושע Yehoshua was much...
...much more of a leader than a נביא *Navi*. שמואל *Shmuel* was
much, was very much a נביא *Navi*, but still the sense of
this like ask the hard questions to God is really identified with
the אורים ותומים *Urim VeTumim*, you know, in this week's פרשה *Parsha*.
So I still think that there's a, that there's that difference, but
I think that the first people that they identified as replacements of
משה Moshe. *Moshe* were יהושע Yehoshua *Yehoshua* and שמואל *Shmuel*.
Even if you remember משה Moshe. *Moshe* as the greatest נביא *Navi*,
but here they went to...
No, but yeah, but I don't understand the distinction. What are you
talking about? It's משה Moshe, *Moshe*, יהושע Yehoshua. *Yehoshua*. If you ask
what's the, you know, who came after משה Moshe *Moshe*, right? You
say יהושע Yehoshua, *Yehoshua*, right? So clearly, yes.
So you're saying the אורים ותומים *Urim VeTumim* in this פרשה *Parsha*
is not to be interpreted literally or as symbolically or as...
No, it is. No, no. So what role the אורים ותומים *Urim
VeTumim* played, that I understand is not a הלכה halacha, *Halacha* role.
Very often, I mean, what we actually find it in the נביאים
*Nevi'im* is that it's used, should we go to war? Should we
do certain things? So it's sort of more actually... More psychological? No,
not psychological, but more sort of actually somewhat, you know, about like
leadership types of questions or, you know, what should we do as
a people? You know, teaching direction, not in terms of teaching הלכה
halacha. *Halacha*.
Oh, okay. It'd be like a Google or call אורים ותומים *Urim
VeTumim*.
Yeah, what does God want us to sort of do in this
case, but not sort of what is the הלכה halacha *Halacha*?
Because it says על פיו ישאלו ועל פיו יצאו ועל פיו יבואו
*Al piv yishalu ve'al piv yetze'u ve'al piv yavo'u*. Right. And that's
usually used in terms of war, right?
Exactly. Exactly. So war was the primary role. Okay, let's keep on
going. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. Okay, אמר ליה
Amar lei, אלעזר *Amar lei Elazar*. Oh, we did that. Okay. אמר
רב יהודה Yehudah אמר רב *Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav*, בשעה שנפטר
משה Moshe. רבינו לגן עדן *Besha'ah sheniftar Moshe Rabbeinu leGan Eden*, when
משה *Moshe* was about to go into גן עדן *Gan Eden*, not
after, but when he's about to, אמר לו ליהושע *Amar lo leYehoshua*,
he said to יהושע Yehoshua *Yehoshua*, שאל ממני כל ספיקות שיש לך
*She'al mimeni kol sefeikot sheyesh lach*, ask me any questions you might
have. You know, I'm about to die, any, you know, I want
to clarify anything that might not be clear to you. אמר לו
*Amar lo*, he said to him, רבי rebbe *Rebbi*, כלום הנחתיך שעה
אחת והלכתי למקום אחר *Kelum hinachticha sha'ah achat vehalachti lemakom acher*, have
I ever left your side and gone somewhere else? ולא כך כתבת
בי בתורה ba-Torah. *Velo kach katavta bi baTorah*, ומשרתו יהושע Yehoshua בן
נון נער לא ימיש מתוך האוהל *Umesharto Yehoshua bin Nun na'ar lo
yamish mitoch ha'ohel*? So I don't need anything. Everything you had to
say, I got it. מיד Miyad תשש כוחו של יהושע *Miyad tashash
kocho shel Yehoshua*, immediately יהושע *Yehoshua*'s, he became weak, his, and, you
know, sort of intellectually, and ונשתכחו ממנו שלוש מאות הלכות halachos. *venishtakechu
mimenu shalosh me'ot halachot*, and he forgot 300 הלכות halachot *Halachot*, ונולדו
לו שבע מאות ספיקות *venoldu lo sheva me'ot sefeikot*, and he had
700 doubts. Now, by the way, why, so why was that? So
I'll tell you what I would have said in a minute, but
if you look at רש"י Rashi *Rashi*, רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says, ועוון
שגרם להחליש דעתו של משה *Ve'avon shegaram lehachlish da'ato shel Moshe*, שהצטער
משה יהושע בעצמו שהיה גדול כמוהו *shehitztayer Moshe Yehoshua be'atzmo shehayah gadol
kamohu*. Very interesting רש"י Rashi *Rashi*. He says that because that really
hurt משה *Moshe*'s feelings. How did it hurt משה *Moshe*'s feelings? You
never left my side. Oh, it hurt משה *Moshe*'s feelings because he
basically said, I got everything I needed from you. Okay? I don't
need you anymore. Go, goodbye, you can die, I got everything I
needed from you. Okay? So it was basically, it was, you know,
obviously somebody's about to die, you want to sort of say, oh
my god, you're about to die, what are we going to do?
We need you. But okay, so that's according to the way רש"י
Rashi *Rashi* explains it, as a question about כבוד *kavod* to משה
*Moshe* and what was the right, you know, interpersonal response at that
moment. But you, you know, I think probably all of you when
you heard that imagined that part of the issue had to do
with a certain amount of arrogance, right? And that part of the
problem here, you know, is that one of the reasons like you
forget, you know, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* about that if you're בעל
גאוה *ba'al ga'avah*, your תורתו משתכחת *Torato mishtakachat*, you think a little
bit too highly of yourself. You know, part of remembering is knowing
that you constantly have to learn, that you constantly have to review
it, you know, that sort of sense of humility is very important,
you know, and when יהושע *Yehoshua* says, even if it's true that
he never left and even if it were true at that moment
he remembered everything, you don't say I don't need anything more, right?
So you grab every opportunity. And I think that that's maybe part
of the moral message here too, not just the way he might
have hurt משה *Moshe*'s feelings.
It's also a bit ironic because the last thing משה רבינו *Moshe
Rabbeinu* would want is for הלכה halacha *Halacha* to be forgotten, you
know, so...
Right, exactly. True, but that was יהושע *Yehoshua*'s fault, not משה *Moshe*'s
fault. משה *Moshe* was trying to preserve it.
And he's also usually so modest, you wouldn't have thought that, you
know, he'd be like so...
All right, anyway, that's the way רש"י Rashi *Rashi* frames it. Fine,
that's the way רש"י Rashi *Rashi* frames it. Anyway, okay, now the
other point is things were forgotten and there were doubts. And again,
this question of what were the doubts? So if you talk, say
that it's all about transmission, so it means 300 things they completely
forgot and 700 things they didn't completely forget, but they forgot certain
parts of it, right? There were doubts about certain aspects of it.
Again, what I would question is, is it all about transmission? So
there are 300 things they forgot and 700 things not that was
forgotten, was perfectly transmitted, but you just had doubts about how to
apply it, how to, you know, understand it, which is what we
understand most of תורה שבעל פה Torah Sheba'al Peh. *Torah Shebe'al Peh*
is. It's not retrieval of what was forgotten, but it's taking what
was remembered and applying it to, you know, to new cases, understanding
its parameters that had not been explicated before. Okay, but again, within
the context of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, the doubts probably more have
to do with doubts of the exactly what was transmitted. Okay, so
יהושע *Yehoshua* forgot all these things or and had these doubts. ועמדו
כל ישראל Yisrael. להורגו *Ve'amdu kol Yisrael lehorgo*. So now all of
the Jewish people wanted to kill him. Now, why did they want
to kill him? So I, you know, you could have thought they
were angry at him. How could you have got those הלכות *Halachot*
lost to us? Right? So it's a type of revenge. רש"י Rashi
*Rashi* says they wanted to kill him because they were demanding... from
him that he's replaced them and he wasn't able to, because right,
he might have asked God and לא בשמים היא lo bashamayim hi.
or whatever, he might have remembered לא בשמים היא. lo bashamayim hi
So anyway, so רש"י Rashi sort of frames it as they wanted
they wanted those הלכות, they wanted to demand it from him. But
it might but the the simple read might just be that they
were angry at him. Anyway, אמר לו הקדוש ברוך הוא. Amar lo
HaKadosh Baruch Hu. So God said to him, לומר לך אי אפשר.
Lomar lach ee efshar. Look, I can't tell you that would solve
the problem here to help to to correct it, to just tell
you, because you know, לא בשמים היא after this point, which really
also underscores why it was a big loss not to have seized
that last opportunity with משה, because after משה things are going to
change in a radical way. Until משה you could go back to
God for this. But after משה it's going to change radically, so
you really should have seized that last opportunity. I can't help you
here. לומר לך אי אפשר. Lomar lach ee efshar. לך וטורדן במלחמה.
Lech u'tordan b'milchama. So how you going to how are you going
to get them away from trying to kill you? Go get them
to direct their anger somewhere else. Go get them to make war.
שנאמר, Shene'emar, right, which by the way, as as we know things
that a lot of sort of politicians like to do. What do
you do if everybody is dissatisfied with the economy and domestic affairs,
whatever? Fine, go have a war. Okay. לך וטורדן במלחמה. Lech u'tordan
b'milchama. שנאמר ויהי אחרי מות משה עבד השם. Shene'emar vayehi acharei mot
Moshe eved Hashem. After משה died, ויאמר השם, Vayomer Hashem, God said
basically you say דע da and that you're about to cross the
ירדן Yarden and then you'll go to war and so on, get
them involved in something else. All right. במתניתא תנא, B'matnita tana, in
our משנה mishna. in in the ברייתא we taught 3,000 הלכות.
According to this?
No. No. יהושע forgot 300 because of what he did. When משה
died, presumably over the mourning of משה there were 3,000 הלכות. These
are similar stories but they're not contradictory, they're focusing on different events.
This is a terrible thing to say go make a war.
Well, look, they were going to make a war anyway.
It's a distraction. We had there was a movie about that.
Right. I know, right, that's what I was sort of referring I
referred to. Right, it's called Wag the Dog or something.
Yes, the movie was called
Wag the Dog.
So people won't complain.
I understand, but it's not saying look, there's another גמרא Gemara in
ברכות Berachos which you'd get more upset about, which is where, you
know, the people of the דוד's David sort of officers or whatever,
you know,
come and complain to him and they say, you know, we're not
making any, you know, the people need פרנסה, parnassa, the economy is
bad. And then he says, okay, let's go make a war. Okay,
but here they were they were that's exactly what they were going
to do anyway next. They were going to go over into ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael and they were going to make war against the
inhabitants. Right, now you can sort of discuss that, but that was
clearly on the agenda. So he wasn't sort of saying let's just
do it for the fun of it. He was basically saying, you
know, let's do what we have to be doing now anyway. So
this was next on the agenda.
But since God was talking to him, he could have then asked
all these questions.
No, but that's what God said, I can't give you the answer.
God said to יהושע.
God said to יהושע, I can't give you the answers.
From now from now on you cannot ask me about הלכה. halacha,
Okay, so anyway.
So don't figure out הלכה, halacha just make war.
No, the question wasn't how are we going to retrieve these. That's
coming up. The question was how are we going to get the
people stop either distracted from being angry at you and trying to
kill you. Okay, so but רבקה, Rivka, the point is again, it's
not as bad as the גמרא Gemara in ברכות Berachos where it's
just was an optional war. Here they were about to do the
war anyway and God says let's move on to the next thing
we have to do, you know, and that's going to and that'll
distract them. All right. So now the גמרא Gemara... continues. במתניתא תנא
אלף ושבע מאות קלין וחמורין. B'matnita tana elef u'shva me'ot kalin v'chamurin.
Here's what they forgot, so we had 3,000, we had 300 and
700. In a ברייתא we taught 1,700 קל וחומרs kal v'chomer וגזירות
שוות u'gezeirot shavot ודקדוקי סופרים v'dikdukei sofrim נשתכחו בימי אבלו של משה.
nishtakchu b'yemei evlo shel Moshe.
Were forgotten in the time of משה. Now this is again, as
I said, the overriding theme in this גמרא Gemara is that it's
all about transmission and this really highlights it because this is the
essence of תורה שבעל פה. Torah Sheba'al Peh. קל וחומר, Kal v'chomer,
גזירה שוה, gezeira shava, דקדוקי סופרים. dikdukei sofrim. What are דקדוקי סופרים
dikdukei sofrim exactly?
I will say in a minute. So anyway, these seem to be
the essence of sort of the rabbinic enterprise of תורה שבעל פה.
Torah Sheba'al Peh It's not just things we call הלכה למשה מסיני.
halacha l'Moshe miSinai. These are things we think it's about engaging the
text with your intellect. Now the גמרא Gemara, says גזירה שוה gezeira
shava you need a מסורה, mesorah, but certain I mean not גזירה
שוה, gezeira shava, but קל וחומר kal v'chomer is the classic thing
you don't need a מסורה. mesorah. And the גמרא gemara is framing
it at all of this they knew and all of this was
forgotten. So really frames the simple sense the גמרא gemara frames the
entire enterprise of תורה שבעל פה Torah she'ba'al peh. as one of
sanctuary of retrieval. But even this stuff which we would have said
is the most sort of part of sort of the rabbinic creativity
and mind applied to the תורה, Torah here is being framed as
part of the מסורה mesorah that was forgotten in the time of
משה. Now what is גזירות שוות? gezeirot shavot? Anyway, that we know,
but קל וחומר kal v'chomer is the opposite extreme. What's דקדוקי סופרים?
dikdukei sofrim? So you could have said it meant rabbinic laws, which
gets to an interesting question. Is the claim even that rabbinic laws
were given over from the time of משה רבינו? Some types of
מדרשים midrashim or whatever suggest that. But רש"י Rashi here says that's
not what דקדוקי סופרים dikdukei sofrim is. If you look at רש"י,
Rashi רש"י says about five lines over the
רבינו גרשום. Rabbeinu Gershom. רש"י says דקדוקי סופרים מפרש בשקלים שעשו התורה
ספירות ספירות כגון... dikdukei sofrim mefaresh b'Shekalim she'asu haTorah sefirot sefirot kegon...
five חטאות המתות, chatot ameitot, five laws about this, 13 things were
said about that, so they're sort of pulling things
together. So they had all these laws but they didn't know how
to group them, is that it? So
רש"י ends this by saying ומאותן
דקדוקין שעדיין לא צירפום u'me'otan dikdukin she'adayin lo tzirfum from those sort
of countings that had not yet been pulled together, נשתכחו בימי
אבלו של משה, nishtakechu b'imei evlo shel Moshe, that was forgotten. So
I didn't exactly get what רש"י was saying. If they hadn't pulled
it together, what did they forget? So they forgot maybe not the
numbers, they forgot actually the laws that would have been the sort
of things that would have been counted, would have been pulled together.
Meaning if they remembered five חטאות המתות chatot ameitot or 13 this,
then they also remember the details. But maybe they actually forgot the
content of that, so it never allowed them to pull it together
and to come up with the number. But anyway, it's not so
clear because as we're going to see and maybe this is even
what the גמרא Gemara is alluding to, one of the doubts was
about the חמישה חטאות המתות. chamisha chatot ameitot. So you could actually
have said from within those things that were counted, they remembered the
number maybe, but they forgot some of the details. Or maybe they
forgot exactly the number because we're going to see in the גמרא
Gemara some of that issue. So anyway, but I think the reason
רש"י is saying שעדיין לא צירפום she'adayin lo tzirfum is דקדוקי סופרים
dikdukei sofrim is the one thing that really indicates that the Rabbis
played a role. It wasn't just transmission. So the role that they
might have played was just pulling them together and giving them a
number and counting them. The actual items and data was already there,
their role of דקדוקי סופרים dikdukei sofrim was to organize it and
to give it a number. And some aspect of that was forgotten
as well. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר
רבי אבהו אף על פי כן, Amar Rabbi Abahu af al pi
chen, even though all of that stuff was forgotten, החזירן עתניאל בן
קנז מתוך פלפולו. hechiziran Osniel ben Kenaz mitokh pilpulo. עתניאל בן קנז,
Osniel ben Kenaz, who we're going to see who he is in
a minute, but he sounds like he might be the brother of
כלב, Kalev, he was able to restore them with his sharpness. And
here we're finally getting again
the use of the human intellect, so don't worry, they were retrieved,
but again the use of the human intellect in serving the goals
of retrieval, right? Not in serving the goals of חידוש chiddush and
of developing, but in serving the goals of retrieval. So he was
able to restore them.
שנאמר, Shene'emar, what were the generations they forgot them again, is that
what happened?
Yeah,
that was the whole point, after the ימי אבלו. yemei evlo. שנאמר
וילכדה עתניאל בן קנז אחי כלב, Shene'emar vayilkeda Osniel ben Kenaz achi
Kalev, that עתניאל בן קנז Osniel ben Kenaz the brother of כלב
Kalev conquered it, which was the city there of
קרית ספר. Kiryat Sefer. Okay, because basically כלב Kalev said whoever conquers
this, I'll give him my daughter. So here עתניאל בן קנז Osniel
ben Kenaz his brother conquered it. ויתן לו את עכסה בתו לאשה.
Vayiten lo et Achsah bito l'ishah. So כלב Kalev did what he
said, he gave him his daughter עכסה Achsah for a wife. So
the point here being that the name of the city is קרית
ספר, Kiryat Sefer, a counting, סופרים, sofrim, right, דקדוקי סופרים dikdukei sofrim
is what we just said. So therefore we say that is what
he was able to restore with his פלפולו. pilpulo.
And sort of his war, the מלחמתה של תורה milchamta shel Torah
as it were, that we sometimes describe that process as a type
of engagement and a battle. So he restored it. ולמה נקרא שמה
עכסה, V'lama nikra shemah Achsah, so now we're going to digress a
little, so why was she called עכסה? Achsah? שכל הרואה אותה כועס
על אשתו. Shekol haro'ah otah ko'eis al ishto. Anybody who saw her
got angry at his wife because she was so beautiful that they
came home and they were angry that their wives weren't as beautiful
as she was. Okay, so then ויהי, vayehi, now the פסוק pasuk,
goes on there after she was given over to עתניאל, Osniel, it
says ויהי בבואה, vayehi b'vo'ah, when she came to be his wife,
ותסיתהו לשאול מאת אביה שדה, vatasitehu lish'ol mei'et aviha sadeh, so she
sort of seduced him, enticed him to ask from her
father כלב Kalev a שדה sadeh like as a dowry.
ותצנח מעל החמור, Vatitznach mei'al hachamor, and she presumably means she lowered
herself from the חמור, chamor, but מאי ותצנח, mai vatitznach, what does
that mean? So the גמרא Gemara is going to interpret ותצנח vatitznach
as a type of like a complaining, a braying.
אמר רבא אמר רבי יצחק אמרה לו, Amar Rava amar Rabbi Yitzchak
amrah lo, she said to
עתניאל, Osniel, מה חמור זה כיון שאין לו מאכל
באבוסו מיד צועק כך אשה שאין לה תבואה בתוך ביתה מיד צועקת.
mah chamor zeh keivan she'ein lo ma'achal b'avuso miyad tzo'ek kakh ishah
she'ein lah tevu'ah b'tokh beitah miyad tzo'eket. So the same way if
a donkey doesn't have food in its trough, immediately it complains, so
you should know you're now starting a life, you have a wife,
and we've got to have, you've got to pay the bills, so
although how much
she needed the water,
right, well that's the פשט pshat of the פסוקים, psukim we'll see
how the גמרא reads it in a minute. So now that you
have a wife you have to know that there's a problem if
there isn't food in the house and we have to take care
of it. Okay, so but of course the way in which it
compares it to doesn't have grain immediately cries out, obviously not so
complimentary, but the גמרא sort of puts this in her own mouth.
She is saying this to him. So to paraphrase... Is it in
a little,
in a slightly nicer way, it's just to say, "Hey buddy, you're
married now, we have to provide for, we have to provide for
the domestic needs of the house, so you should ask my father
for a field." Let's keep on going. ותאמר תנה לי ברכה. Vatomer
tnah li bracha. So here's what she said to her father: "Give
me a well, כי ארץ הנגב נתתני. ki eretz hanegev netatani. You've
given me a dry land." So now what does this mean? So
now we're going to translate this into the way we frame this.
So here's what she says to her father: בית שמנוגב מכל טובה.
Bayis shemenugav mikol tova. You have, I have now a house that
is dried from all good. ונתת לי, Venatata li, instead of giving
me that, now the פשט pshat of the פסוקים is, "Please give
me these wellsprings of water." But the גמרא is reading it that
that's not what she said. She said, "You gave me a dry
house and instead, what have you given me? You've given me גולות
מים, Gulos mayim, sort of springs of water." What does that mean?
So it means אדם שאין בו אלא תורה בלבד. Adam she'ein bo
ela Torah bilvad. Says, "What good did you do me, Dad? You
gave me a תלמיד חכם. Talmid chacham. Who needs a תלמיד חכם?
Talmid chacham? How am I going to put food on the table?"
"Yeah, but כלב, Kalev, you
just conquered a whole city."
"Alright, we are reading this in the context of him being a
תלמיד חכם." Talmid chacham. Okay, so here is the woman, the practical,
worried about the household, and she says to him, "Hey buddy, you
gotta ask my father for a field, because all you know how
to do is sit and learn, but who's going to provide food?"
And she goes to her father and says, "You've given me a
house that's empty of all goodness. It's very nice, he sits and
learns all the time, but who's going to put food on the
table?"
So that's what she said to her father. So let's see what
the response was. ויתן לה כלב את גולות עליות ואת גולות תחתיות.
Vayiten lah Kalev es gulos eliyos v'es gulos tachtiyos. He gave him
the upper and the lower sort of springs. So what does this
mean? אמר ליה, it said to me, now there are גרסאות girsaos
that דר עליונים, dar elyonim, that lives in the supreme levels, but
that would be God, so and that doesn't fit the context. So
the other גרסא girsa here is מי שכל רזי, mi shekol razei,
the person that all the secrets of עליונים ותחתונים, elyonim vesachtonim, who
knows all the secrets of above and below, meaning this huge תלמיד
חכם Talmid chacham who's your husband, who was able to restore what
we forgot in the time of משה, who knows all the secrets
of the world, so him יבקש ממנו מזונות. yevakesh mimenu mezonos. You
should ask from him for your sustenance. Or there's two ways to
read this. There are two ways to read this. Either I'm saying
it, okay, one is, here you have this תלמיד חכם, Talmid chacham,
he knows everything in the world, he can provide for you. How's
he going to provide for you? So רש"י says, if you look
at רש"י top of the second column of לשון כלה, Lashon Kallah,
יבקש ממנו מזונות דודאי לא יצטרך. yevakesh mimenu mezonos d'vadai lo yitztarech.
You're not going to need to worry about food. Why not? דכתיב
בה, Dechsiv bah, it says by it, what's בה? bah? By the
תורה, Torah, no, by the תורה, Torah אשת חיל, Eishes chayil, but
framed here implicit in רש"י is the תורה, Torah okay, היתה כאניות
סוחר. haysa k'oniyos socheir. So if you know the תורה, Torah. ממרחק
תביא לחמה, mimerchak tavi lachmah, if you have a husband that's a
תלמיד חכם, Talmid chacham, you'll be provided for. Don't worry, God will
provide. Okay, that, and again it's ironic taking אשת חיל, Eishes chayil,
which is about the woman who's concerned about the domestic aspects of
the house and who makes sure that there are things that are
provided, and it's, it's all about תורה torah and if your husband's
a תלמיד חכם, Talmid chacham, it'll be taken care of. That's what
רש"י says. רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom says the following. He says,
"I've given you a person that knows all the secrets of the
heaven, מרוב חכמתו, merov chochmaso, from his great wisdom, ולא
דייך, velo dayach, that's not enough, ועוד מבקשת ממנו מזונות? ve'od mevakeshes
mimenu mezonos? It's not enough you have a תלמיד חכם, Talmid chacham,
you also want food? You want everything? Okay, you should know what
your priorities are, wife. If you're married to a
תלמיד חכם, Talmid chacham, not that that's going to magically put food
on the table, but that should be much more important than having
somebody that has a good פרנסה." parnassah. Okay, so a little more,
a little less of a metaphysical answer to that.
ונתת לי גולות מים, Venatata li gulos mayim, that was actually part
of the פסוק, Pasuk right?
Yeah, she was asking for that. Okay, and then he gave her
these. Okay, so that's again a fascinating little digression about תלמיד חכם
Talmid chacham and the אשת חיל Eishes chayil of course reminds one
of that famous joke where the punchline, without just the punchline, the
guy sitting at a table,
whatever, and somebody says to him,
"Says חיים, Chaim, how do you provide? You sit in ישיבה yeshiva
all day, and what do you put food on?" He says, "ברוך
השם, Baruch Hashem, the אייבישטער Eibishter provides." He says, "Yes, but you
have five kids. What do you?" "ברוך השם, Baruch Hashem, the אייבישטער
Eibishter provides." And goes on and on. So then they say to
the mother, "What do you think of your son-in-law?" She says, "I
don't really care for his attitude, not working, he doesn't provide." And
says to the father, "What do you think of your son-in-law?" Says,
"I love him, he thinks I'm the אייבישטער." Eibishter.
So anyway,
alright, so okay, so the אייבישטער Eibishter will provide. That's the way
רש"י says it, the תורה torah will make it happen. And
רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom says even if it doesn't happen, that should
be much more important. Alright, anyway, now the גמרא goes on.
So that was עכסה, Achsah, by the way, עכסה Achsah is a
very good female, a strong figure.
Oh, absolutely, yeah.
She's telling her husband, "This is, my father, he gave, we have
this field, but it doesn't have water."
Exactly, exactly, yeah. She is a strong figure. And that's sort of
ironic in that אשת חיל, Eishes chayil, she's like that אשת חיל
Eishes chayil who strongly is there for her family or whatever.
What is she saying?
You
know, it's not enough that you give me all this תורה, torah
we still have to live.
Right. Right. Right. I agree. Anyway, okay, fine. So then the גמרא
continues.
וכלב בן קנז, V'Chalev ben Kenaz, so it says that this עתניאל
בן קנז Othniel ben Kenaz was כלב's Chalev brother, which would mean
that כלב Chalev was the son of קנז. Kenaz. Is that really
true? ולא כלב בן יפנה הוא? V'lo Chalev ben Yefunneh hu? We
know in the תורה torah he's called כלב בן יפנה. Chalev ben
Yefunneh. So the גמרא says no. מאי יפנה? Mai Yefunneh? שפנה מעצת
מרגלים. She-pannah me-atzat meraglim. That wasn't his literal name, that was just
descriptive. It means that he turned away from the מרגלים. meraglim. But
his real the real his real name was כלב בן Chalev ben
what do you call it? בן קנז. ben Kenaz. So the גמרא
says like this. ועתניאל בן קנז הוא? V'Othniel ben Kenaz hu? Are
you really saying he's the son of קנז? Kenaz? הא בן חצרון
הוא. Ha ben Chetzron hu. He's the son of חצרון. Chetzron. How
do you know? דכתיב, Dichtiv, וכלב בן חצרון הוליד את עזובה. v'Chalev
ben Chetzron holid et Azuvah. כלב בן חצרון Chalev ben Chetzron gave
birth to עזובה. Azuvah. פסוק pasuk? in דברי הימים, Divrei HaYamim, and
presumably the same כלב. Chalev. So אמר רבא, Amar Rava, okay, you're
right. He his father wasn't קנז. Kenaz. חורגיה דקנז הוה. Chorgei d'Kenaz
hava. He was קנז's Kenaz stepson. So he was עתניאל's Othniel brother,
meaning he was his half-brother. Okay, so כלב's Chalev mother married קנז
Kenaz and then and then from there עתניאל Othniel was born. Okay,
so עתניאל Othniel was בן קנז ben Kenaz and עתניאל Othniel was
כלב's Chalev brother, but כלב's Chalev father was not קנז. Kenaz. כלב's
Chalev father was חצרון, Chetzron, not יפנה Yefunneh according to
יהודה Yehudah who died and then the גמרא...
Right, exactly. Okay, anyway. So גמרא says like this. תנא, now that
we're talking about עתניאל בן קנז, Othniel ben Kenaz, הוא עתניאל הוא
יעבץ. hu Othniel hu Yavetz. The same עתניאל Othniel is referred to
also in in other places there's a there's a figure by the
name of יעבץ. Yavetz. We're saying it's the same person. ומה שמו?
U-mah shemo? What was his real name? All of these are descriptive
names. His real name was יהודה אחי שמעון, Yehudah achi Shimon, יהודה
the brother of שמעון. Shimon. ושמו, V'shmo, what does that mean? עתניאל
שענאו אל. Othniel she-annao El. עתניאל Othniel
because he was answered by אל. El. And we'll see what that
means in a minute. יעבץ, Yavetz, יעבץ Yavetz means שיעץ וריבץ תורה.
she-ya'atz v'ribbetz Torah. יעבץ, Yavetz, יעץ וריבץ תורה. ya'atz v'ribbetz Torah. He
advised about and he spread תורה torah in ישראל. Yisrael, So again
emphasizing him as a תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham. Okay, ומנלן שענאו אל?
U-minalan she-annao El? How do we know God answered him? דכתיב, Dichtiv,
ויקרא יעבץ לאלהי ישראל. vayikra Yavetz l'Elohei Yisrael. יעבץ Yavetz called out
and now we're saying יעבץ Yavetz is עתניאל. Othniel. He called out
to the God of ישראל, לאמר, lemor, אם ברך תברכני, im barech
tevarcheni, if you bless me, והרבית את גבולי, v'hirbita et gevuli, and
you broaden my boundaries, והיתה ידך עמי, v'hayetah yadcha immi, what's your
פסוק? pasuk והיתה ידך עמי, v'hayetah yadcha immi, your hand is with
me, ועשית מרעה, v'asita me-ra'ah, and you do מרעה, me-ra'ah, which is
a little unclear what it means, we'll see in the גמרא, it
could mean מרעה me-ra'ah you prevent bad from happening to me, but
anyway, לבלתי עצבי, l'vilti otzbi, to to prevent me from being anguished,
troubled, then it doesn't say if he doesn't say what will happen
if you do this, but he basically asked this from God. And
the end of the פסוק pasuk says, ויבא אלהים את אשר שאל.
vayave Elohim et asher sha'al. God gave him what he asked. Okay,
now we're going to translate it. Again, interesting thing, the simple sense
of the פסוק pasuk is that it's talking about land, and we
are going to translate it because it's about עתניאל Othniel and his
problem as we saw with his wife is that he didn't care
about he wasn't, you know, he could care less about worldly stuff.
So what he's really asking is about תורה. torah So let's take
a look.
So what's he saying?
Okay, אם ברך תברכני, im barech tevarcheni, if you bless me, בתורה.
והרבית את גבולי, v'hirbita et gevuli, בתלמידים. b'talmidim. So what does it
mean to expand my borders? It means with students, not with property.
That's how you spread out and, you know, your teaching spreads. והיתה
ידך עמי, v'hayetah yadcha immi, and your hand is with me, שלא
ישתכח תלמודי מלבי. she-lo yishtakkach talmudi mi-libbi. That your teaching is not
forgotten from my heart. Going back to the theme of remembering. He
was the one that retrieved it even though he used his intellect
to retrieve it and maybe could retrieve it again with his intellect,
but he didn't want it to be forgotten.
Okay, ועשית מרעתי. v'asita me-ra'ati. So what does that mean? שיזדמנו לי
רעים. she-yizdamnu li re'im. So the word מרעים me-re'im like רעים, re'im,
friends, that I have colleagues כמותי. kamoti. People want not only students,
they want colleagues, colleagues that share their values, colleagues that, you know,
share their commitments and so on, intellectual colleagues. So I want to
have colleagues. לבלתי עצבי, l'vilti otzbi, that I should not sort of,
you know, lead to anguish and trouble, שלא ישגבני יצר הרע מלשנות.
she-lo yasgivani yetzer hara mi-lishnot. That my יצר הרע yetzer hara should
not sort of seduce me into to change my path. You know,
may you know, I believe I'm on the right path, I know
later I might, you know, we know we sort of change our
minds about things as we continue in our lives, maybe I'll decide
oh maybe I actually should devote more time to making a living
or something like that. No, I ask for your help that I
sort of stay firm in my path. והכי דעשית פשוטו לבטל מתלמוד
תורה. v'hachi d'asita p'shuto l'vattel mi-talmud Torah. That not, you know, not
cause me to to sort of be מבטל. me-vattel. But I think
it could also just mean not cause me to change my priorities.
Okay. אם אתה עושה כן מוטב. im attah oseh ken mutav. Now
again, the problem is that the פסוק pasuk doesn't say the end
of the if. It just says God, if you do this. If
what? Then and and if not what? If so then what and
if not what? So if you do this, then it will be
good.
ואם לאו, v'im lav, הריני הולך. hareni holech. exactly לנססי לשאול lenesisi
lishol or לגיססי לשאול, legisisi lishol, I will go down in my
trembling into the depths meaning like I go שאול Sheol and to
the depths. Okay. I could just you know my life is over.
This is what my life means to me and give this to
me and if not I might as well just die right now
and go down into the depths you know frustrated and whatever you
know whatever not frustrated is too light of a word. Okay. מיד
oh he was so insistent on it was so important to it
him ויבא אלהים את אשר שאל vayavei elohim et asher sha'al God
gave him what he asked for. כיוצא בדבר אתה אומר Kayotzei badavar
atah omer similarly you say another פסוק pasuk where we have the
same idea רש ואיש תככים נפגשו rash ve-ish tichachim nifgashu a poor
person and a man of תככים tichachim not exactly clear what that
means נפגשו nifgashu they they encounter themselves מאיר עיני שניהם השם me'ir
einei sheneihem hashem God enlightens the eyes of both of them. What
does that mean?
בשעה שהתלמיד הולך אצל רבו Besha'ah she-hatalmid holech eitzel rabbo a student
comes to his רבי rebbe ואומר לו למדני תורה ve-omer lo lamdeni
torah teach me תורה Torah,
אם למדו im limdo מאיר עיני שניהם השם me'ir einei sheneihem hashem
if so then God will make sure that not only that the
רבי rebbe is enlightened and his student is enlightened and it'll all
be good. ואם לאו Ve-im lav if he refuses him תורה עשיר
ורש נפגשו ashir varash nifgashu God is it's a poor a poor
person and a rich person encountered ועושה כולם השם ve-oseh kulam hashem
God makes both of them. What does that mean God makes both
of them? He means God could easily reverse their fates. מי שעשה
חכם לזה עושה אותו טפש Mi she-asah chacham la-zeh oseh oto tipeish
if he make this one smart he'll become dumb. טפש לזה עושה
אותו חכם Tipeish la-zeh oseh oto chacham and the one that was
not as informed he will become the wise one. So the point
is here what? That here if you are insistent on your learning
then nothing will stand in your way. The people a people should
help you out like עתניאל בן קנז Otni'el ben Kenaz was insistent
on his learning God helped him out and if somebody doesn't want
to help you out God is going to make sure that you
will succeed sort of regardless. So here's the important point you know
she his wife was insistent on the פרנסה parnasah you know but
she was given an answer you should worry about that. He's insistent
on his learning and God answers him.
Okay.
And now the גמרא says okay also you sort of wonder okay
about the תלמיד talmid asking the רבי and so on is it
a little echo to the יהושע and משה story where יהושע did
not demand the תורה use the opportunity to ask the תורה from
the משה. Okay.
Where are we? Okay. זו משנת רבי נתן Zu mishnat rabbi natan
that's how רבי נתן rabbi natan reads the whole case. רבי יהודה
הנשיא אומר Rabbi yehudah hanasi omer רבי יהודה הנשיא rabbi yehudah hanasi
says אם ברך תברכני im bareich tevarcheini no no no maybe actually
he was a little bit influenced by his wife and here actually
he's not asking he doesn't say that I'm connecting the דרשות drashot
but here he's not asking for תורה okay here is what he's
asking for God if you bless me פריה ורביה piryah verivyah if
you give me a lot of children והרבית את גבולי vehirbeita et
gevuli and you and you expand my borders בבנים ובבנות bevanim uvevanot
again sons and daughters I don't know exactly how it's exactly different
פריה ורביה piryah verivyah maybe that they survive better it's connecting back
to
the wife story
no no this is straight what the גמרא is saying yeah okay
and you give me sons and daughters והיתה ידך עמדי vehayetah yadcha
imadi and now it's all very nice you have a lot of
kids how are you going to provide for them במשא ומתן bemassa
umattan
that you actually help me be successful in business so here actually
maybe he heard his wife a little bit okay ועשית מרעתי ve'asita
meira'ati שלא יהא בי מיחוש ראש ומיחוש אזנים ומיחוש עינים shelo yehei
bi meichush rosh umeichush oznayim umeichush einayim that I don't have headaches
and eye aches meaning I should have good health so here he's
worried about very basic sort of domestic things so
how do you translate מרעתי meira'ati
save me from evil as opposed to the word before translating it
as מרעים merei'im as friends לבלתי עצבי levilti atzvi that I should
not you know be be anguished שלא ישיגני יצר הרע למשנות shelo
yasigeini yetzer hara limshanot so again that the יצר הרע yetzer hara
should not cause me to change my priority this is really what
I have to be focused on so it's quite fascinating right because
here according to this presumably the עתניאל בן קנז Otni'el ben Kenaz
who restored the entire תורה he also understood the pragmatic aspects and
he actually said God I need you to make sure that I
don't forget these things so it sounds like this is sort of
the nice complement to the story about the wife the interesting thing
I also wonder is you know that that is what רבי יהודה
הנשיא rabbi yehudah hanasi said now you would think that רבי יהודה
הנשיא rabbi yehudah hanasi you know on the one hand if he's
the נשיא nasi he doesn't have to worry about making a good
living and so on but on the other hand he also means
that he doesn't live in a you know in a sort of
in a cloister and in a castle in the sky so he
he lives in the real world so he understands the sort of
if you would the wife's concern and he understands that even תלמידי
חכמים talmidei chachamim have to worry about putting bread on the table
although there are other stories where he didn't realize exactly what some
of the you know how some of the תנאים tannaim were actually
what they had to do in order to make a פרנסה parnasah
but at least he understands that that's part of what it means
you know part of one's responsibilities okay אם אתה עושה כן im
atah oseh kein if you do that מוטב mutav it'll all be
good ואם לאו ve'im lav and if you don't God won't do
that הריני הולך בנססי לשאול hareini holech benisisi lishol I will go
down in sort of my my trembling you know my anguish into
the depths so what happened ויבא אלהים את אשר שאל vayavei elohim
et asher sha'al God gave him what he asked כיוצא בדבר אתה
אומר kayotzei badavar atah omer similarly you say רש ואיש תככים נפגשו
rash ve'ish tichachim nifgashu מאיר עיני שניהם השם me'ir einei sheneihem hashem
again the poor and the rich person encounter בשעה שאני הולך אצל
בעל הבית besha'ah she'ani holech eitzel ba'al habayit so now it's about
practically providing for the house so a poor person who is insistent
on understands his responsibility to provide for his household, so he goes
to somebody and asks for help. אמר פרנסני, Amar parneseini, provide for
me, whether that means give me צדקה, tzedaka, whether that means give
me a job, but he turns to somebody for help because he
understands his responsibilities. אם מפרנסו מוטב, Im mefarneso mutav, if he helps
him good, ואם לאו, ve'im lav, if he refuses to help him,
עשיר ורש נפגשו עושה כולם ה', Ashir varash nifgashu ose chulam Hashem,
God makes both of them. מי שעשה עשיר לזה עושה עני, עני
לזה עושה עשיר, Mi she'asa ashir laze ose ani, ani laze ose
ashir, God can reverse their fortunes. And again a more literal read
of the פסוק about rich and poor, not rich and poor in
תורה, but rich and poor in wealth. But again the emphasis of
if you have to understand your responsibilities and be insistent on them,
demand them, demand them from God, demand them from people, and in
the end,
it'll work out if you have the right priorities and don't waver
from them. Okay, that was a fascinating little digression. We now have
about five minutes. Let's try to do a little part here about
the הלכה. halacha אמר רבי שמעון, Amar Rabbi Shimon, מה מצינו, ma
matzinu, so all of this was about
the חמש חטאות המתות chamesh chata'ot hametot and how one, some aspect
of that was forgotten. So now we're actually going to turn back
to that. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. רבי שמעון אומר. Rabbi Shimon omer.
חמש חטאות מתות. Chamesh chata'ot metot. We know that there are five
חטאות chata'ot that have to be let die when they occur by
an individual. ולד חטאת ותמורת חטאת וחטאת שמתו בעליה וחטאת שנתכפרו בעליה
וחטאת שעברה שנתה. Velad chatat utmurat chatat vechatat shemetu ba'aleha vechatat shenitkapru
ba'aleha vechatat she'avra shnata. A child of a חטאת, chatat, a exchange,
a תמורה, tmura, the owners die, another קרבן korban was brought, or
it was no longer a year old. אי אתה יכול לומר ולד
חטאת בציבור. I ata yachol lomar velad chatat betzibur. Now half of
these don't apply in communal. There's not a ולד חטאת velad chatat
in a ציבור, tzibur, a child, לפי שאין חטאת נקבה בציבור, lefi
she'ein chatat nekeiva betzibur, because communal חטאות chata'ot are all male, not
female. ואי אתה יכול לומר תמורת חטאת בציבור. Ve'i ata yachol lomar
tmurat chatat betzibur. You can't have a תמורה, tmura, לפי שאין ציבור
עושה תמורה. lefi she'ein tzibur ose tmura. We learned that you cannot
have a ציבור tzibur that doesn't do תמורה. tmura. ואי אתה יכול
לומר חטאת שמתו בעליה בציבור, Ve'i ata yachol lomar chatat shemetu ba'aleha
betzibur, and you can't have the fact that the owners died, you
don't have that scenario, לפי שאין ציבור מתים, lefi she'ein tzibur metim,
because the ציבור tzibur doesn't die. So therefore three of the five
only apply to a יחיד. yachid. Once that's true, we know the
whole group only applies to a יחיד. yachid. So therefore שנתכפרו בעליה
ושעברה שנתה, shenitkapru ba'aleha veshe'avra shnata, when it's no longer a year
old and when the owners were atoned for, לא מצינו, lo matzinu,
we don't know what the הלכה halacha is with them. Do they
apply to the יחיד yachid or do they
only apply to the ציבור tzibur or only to the יחיד? yachid?
So he says, יכול יהו נוהגות בין ביחיד בין בציבור, Yachol yehu
nohagot bein beyachid bein betzibur, maybe they should apply equally to both
and in both cases you say let it die? אמרת, Amarta, ילמד
סתום מן המפורש, yilamed satum min hameforash,
let's learn what's not explicated from what is explicated. מה מפורש ביחיד,
Ma meforash beyachid, the three of them we know only apply to
a individual חטאת, chatat, ולא בציבור, velo betzibur, so even these two,
אף שנתכפרו בעליה ושעברה שנתה ביחיד דבריהם אמורים ולא בציבור. af shenitkapru
ba'aleha veshe'avra shnata beyachid divreihem amurim velo betzibur. So these two also,
if three of the five apply only to a יחיד, yachid, then
the other two also apply only like that. So let's, I want
to go like three minutes over and just get to the משנה.
Okay, this goes very fast. So the גמרא says, וכי דנים אפשר
משאי אפשר? Vechi danim efshar mishe'i efshar? Can you learn something that's
possible from something not possible? Three don't apply because you don't have
the scenario. The other two might apply because the scenario can occur.
How do you know that just because the three the scenario doesn't
happen, it means that the other two don't apply בציבור? betzibur? So
אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish, and here we tie it back
to the thing about forgetting, ארבע נשנו להם והעמידו אותם על חמש.
Arba nishnu lahem vehe'emidu otam al chamesh. No, they had a מסורה
mesora that four חטאות chata'ot were מתות. metot. Now first of all
he didn't have to say that, as תוספות Tosafot points out, you
could have said the מסורה mesora is five חטאות chata'ot were מתות,
metot, but actually there is a question that maybe they didn't have
all of it במסורה. bemesora. Maybe the only things that they, they
only knew four. They didn't know which one was the fifth. They
knew that there was a fifth one, they didn't know which was
the fifth one, they knew four out of the five had to
die, one could graze, but they had to say all five had
to die because they didn't know what the, they didn't know which
was the fifth, which goes back to forgetting the דקדוקי סופרים, dikdukei
sofrim, the exact numbers. So they knew four, four out of the
five, they didn't know which four. Okay, but the point is, he
didn't even have to say that, but he is admitting that one
they didn't know. Nevertheless, they knew four were הלכה למשה מסיני halacha
leMoshe miSinai they die, and the assumption was that these were a
group. It's all or nothing. So where does the four apply? It
can only apply in a case of a יחיד. yachid. It can't
apply in a case of a ציבור. tzibur. ואי סלקא דעתך בציבור,
Ve'i salka daitach betzibur, if that הלכה halacha that four had to
die were said by ציבור, tzibur, you wouldn't have had all four.
הנך מי איתנהו בציבור? Hanech mi itneihu betzibur? You don't have at
least two of the four wouldn't at least apply בציבור. betzibur. אלא
על כרחך ילמד סתום מן המפורש. Ela al korchacha yilamed satum min
hameforash. We have to say that since we know that some of
these only apply ביחיד beyachid and the assumption is these are as
a group and if one of them applies they all apply, so
therefore it must have been the הלכות were said ביחיד beyachid and
not בציבור. betzibur. Well, one more, one more, what did
רבא Rava say back to that?
He said it wasn't as a group, it could be where it's
relevant it's relevant. רב נתן אומר, Rav Natan omer, רב נתן Rav
Natan goes to the opposite extreme which again re-emphasizes the whole theme
of forgetting, אחת נשנית להם. achat nishnit lahem.
Really the מסורה mesora was one חטאת chatat have to die, one
of these five. Four have to graze, but they completely forgot which
one. They completely forgot which one, they said all five have to
die. Okay, but the real הלכה, the real מסורה mesora was only
one. So again that theme of
forgetfulness. So now, ולפי האי סדרא גמירי, ulefi hai sidra gemiri, the
גמרא says why didn't they just sort of ask themselves, why did
they have to translate... Why did they ask themselves was this one
that had to let die, was this something that applies only ביחיד
beyachid or both ביחיד beyachid and בציבור? betzibur? And if they could
remember that, then if it applied only ביחיד beyachid they'd only have
to extend it to three because there are only three that apply
only ביחיד. beyachid. If it applied only both ביחיד beyachid and בציבור
betzibur they'd only have to make it two because there are only
two things that apply to both. So why wouldn't they at least
remember whether it was part of the group that was only individual
or the group that was ביחיד yachid and בציבור? tzibur? So the
גמרא says אי ביחיד אי בציבור, ei beyachid ei betzibur, let's try
to at least remember that aspect of it, which group was it
a part of? But it says you know what? תרתי שכיח שכו.
trei shchiach shchu. They forgot two things. Okay, they forgot number one,
which was the one, and they forgot even of the one, which
group it was a part of. So they didn't know whether they
forgot all they remembered was that there was one. And therefore they
had to apply it to all five. Now how does that lead
to this argument? Because although you didn't have a group of four
that had to die, you had the opposite group. You knew that
there was a group of four that was a unified group that
had to be allowed to graze. Okay, and that group you never
have four by the ציבור. tzibur. So that group of four that
had to be allowed to graze was certainly said by the יחיד.
yachid. וקשיא להו. V'kashya lehu. And they had so so they and
they and they were bothered. אי סלקא דעתך בציבור, Ei salka daitach
betzibur, if this הלכה was said by ציבור, tzibur, הנך מי איתנהו
בציבור? hanach mi itnehu betzibur? You don't have all four by ציבור,
tzibur, right? ציבור tzibur at most has two of these scenarios. אלא,
Ella, when this הלכה was said that four have to graze, שמע
מינה יומא ציתא מפורש. shma mina yoma tzita m'forash.
It has to be that those four were said by the יחיד.
yachid. Once that's true, so the whole הלכה was said by the
יחיד. yachid. The four graze and one dies. מה מפורש ביחיד ולא
בציבור אף סתם ביחיד ולא בציבור. Ma m'forash beyachid v'lo betzibur af
stam beyachid v'lo betzibur.
So the same way some of them applied only to the יחיד,
yachid, they all apply only to the יחיד. yachid. And therefore we
know either because we know that the הלכה five have to die
is a unified group and that applies ביחיד, beyachid, so if some
apply they all apply, it's only ביחיד. beyachid. Or if the four
that graze as a unified group, but if it's assumed a unified
group and since some of them are only ביחיד, beyachid, the whole
group is only ביחיד. beyachid. So again the answer is we have
this מסורה, mesorah, this was the group, we assume they all apply
only to one, you know, that they have to come as a
group and they can only come as the group ביחיד. beyachid. But
again the fascinating thing is going back to the theme that it's
saying that not only did the issue they debated about the ציבור
tzibur whether it dies was debated, but even the basic thing that
we say הלכה למשה מסיני, halacha l'Moshe miSinai, חמש חטאות מתות, chamesh
chataot meitot, really הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'Moshe miSinai was one or
four and they just forgot it. So they had to extend it
to five which really again reemphasizes that whole theme of forgetfulness and
really is a whole, you know, obvious evidence against the רמב"ם Rambam
that says that there was never debates about הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha
l'Moshe miSinai. But here we see and here we see that there
actually were problems with transmission. This whole גמרא is about the challenges
of transmission and emphasizing that as the primary endeavor of תורה שבעל
פה.
That's all for tonight.
We'll don't ask us tomorrow what we
said today.